<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tender visitation of love to professors and profane, but especially to the inhabitants of the town of Waymouth. With some directions how they may try themselves, whether they are yet in their sins, or whether they are come to him that makes an end of sin. Also a warning to all sorts of people, that they may repent of the evil of their wayes whilest the day of mercy lasteth, least repentance be hid from their eyes. Howl ye inhabitants of the earth, for the day of vengeance is at hand, the Lord will stain the glory of all flesh. Being written from the breathings of life, by a hand-maid of the Lord, S. R.</title>
            <author>S. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R77</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831110</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831110</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35572</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2039:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tender visitation of love to professors and profane, but especially to the inhabitants of the town of Waymouth. With some directions how they may try themselves, whether they are yet in their sins, or whether they are come to him that makes an end of sin. Also a warning to all sorts of people, that they may repent of the evil of their wayes whilest the day of mercy lasteth, least repentance be hid from their eyes. Howl ye inhabitants of the earth, for the day of vengeance is at hand, the Lord will stain the glory of all flesh. Being written from the breathings of life, by a hand-maid of the Lord, S. R.</title>
                  <author>S. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Heading on p. 3 reads: I have a long time kept silence, now will I write that I may be eased, I will declare that I may be unburthened.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Weymouth and Melcombe Regis (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35572:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35572:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Tender Viſitation of Love TO PROFESSORS and PROFANE, But eſpecially to the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>WAYMO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With ſome directions how they may try themſelves, whether they are yet in their ſins, or whether they are come to him that makes an end of ſin.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Warning to all ſorts of people, that they may repent of the evil of their wayes whileſt the day of Mercy laſteth, leaſt Repentance be hid from their eyes.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Howl ye Inhabitants of the Earth, for the day of vengeance is at hand, the Lord will ſtain the glory of all fleſh.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Being written from the breathings of Life, by a hand-maid of the Lord, <hi>S. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35572:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35572:2"/>
            <head>I have a long time kept ſilence, now will I write that I may be eaſed, I will declare that I may be unbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened.</head>
            <p>O You profeſſors, the Lord God in meaſure hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me your ſtates and conditions, which is very bad and dangerous for you to go on in; O you are all of you poaſting the very way to Deſtructon, <hi>a black day</hi> hangs over your heads, you are all of you as people in the dark, you are ſeeking the way of the Lord where it is not to be found; O your wayes and doings are not good, they are not according to the Truth of the Living God, you have ayrie light vain ſpirits, you ſpeak of the things you know not; you are like people who are dreaming of things, and when the ſleep is over, behold it was not ſo; you have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſhew or ſhadow of truth, but the Subſtance you know not; you are in the many wayes, where no true peace is to be found, but Rents and Diviſions, you have choſen lying vanities, and you go on in the imaginations of your own hearts, chuſing that which the Lord hath no pleaſure in, but his Righteous Soul is vexed, even from day to day.</p>
            <p>O you barren Trees, you cumber the ground, leaves are found on you, but no fruits at all, <hi>The Lord God will ſhake off your Leaves, and your Branches ſhall wither, you ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to cover your ſelves withal, the very foundation ſhall be ſhaken whereon you ſtand, then may you wiſh that the Mountains or Hills could hide you from the Wrath of the Lord God, he will ſpeedily avenge himſelf upon all the workers of Iniquity.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſtout-hearted men and women, leave off doing that which is evil, and repent, make no delay, for the <hi>time is ſhort,</hi> &amp; the day of the Lord God <hi>is at hand,</hi> wherein all your wayes words works and actions are to be tryed, of what profeſſion ſo ever you are of, the Lord will viſit you, he will prove all your wayes by <hi>Fire,</hi> and there is nothing ſhall be able to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35572:3"/>ſtand in that day but that which is <hi>pure of God,</hi> which hath known the day of burning and purifying by <hi>fire,</hi> of ſuch the ſecond death ſhall have no power, but all Profeſſions which are out of the life and power of the truth of the living God, ſuch I ſay ſhall periſh and die, the Lord hath no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them, they are as a loathſome thing which hath an ill ſavour in his noſtrils.</p>
            <p>O you Profeſſors, your many long prayers the Lord hath no regard unto; your holy Sabbath Daies, and your ſolemn Feaſt-daies are as an Abominable thing, the Lord hath no pleaſure in them, they are no more to him, then if you offered Swines fleſh, or did cut off a Doggs neck, the Lord is even wearied with your Sacrifices, your hearts are unclean before him, read <hi>Cain</hi> the Murderer which ſlew his Brother, the juſt <hi>Abel</hi> who was born after the Spirit, I ſay <hi>Cain</hi> which ſlew the juſt, he brought alſo a Sacrifice and offered it unto the Lord even as <hi>Abel</hi> did, whom the Lord had regard unto, but unto <hi>Cain,</hi> and to his off ring, the Lord had no regard, for the ſame Nature which ſlew the juſt one, I ſay that ſame Nature can offer Sacrifices, the ſame Nature which went out into the Tranſgreſſion, which was the firſt Nature, I ſay the ſame Nature can Pray and ſing, and ſpeak many great ſwelling Words, but this the Lord hath no regard un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>O why will you die, why will you die? Why will you ſtand out any longer? Why will you put the day afar off? Are you reſolved through wilfulneſs to die in your ſins? hath not the Lord ſet good and evil before your eyes, and will you ſtill chuſe the evil, and deſpiſe the good? O you Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Town of <hi>Waymouth,</hi> the Lord hath had a tender pitty towards you, O your warnings hath been many by the Lords Servants and hand-maids, but you have made it as a leight thing, and you have called the Lords Meſſengers and Servants the Devils,) and ſome have ſaid that the Devil ſent them, but the day will come when many of you ſhall ſay, &amp; be made to confeſs, that many of you have been warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Lord out of their mouths, and many ſhall ſtand as witneſſes in the day of God, when his wrath ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed againſt the unrighteouſneſſe of every man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35572:3"/>I ſay in that day many ſhall ſtand as living witneſſes againſt you, becauſe the Lord hath warned many of you out of their mouths, although you have deſpiſed the reproof of the Lord, and caſt his Law and his Counſel behind your backs; O may it not juſtly be ſaid to you, as the Lord ſaid to a people in the daies of old, <hi>becauſe you would not receive my Counſel, nor regard my repoof, therefore</hi> the Lord ſaid to that people, <hi>he would laugh at their calamities, and mock when fear cometh upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Awake, awake, you who are aſleep in ſecurity, I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and come forth out of your graves, the Lord our God is riſen, he hath ſounded his Alarm to the Nations, he hath uttered his voice to the ends of the Earth, the remote <hi>Iſlands</hi> hath heared his ſound, <hi>the graves are opened, and many dead bodies are raiſed to ſing prayſes to the Lord for ever and ever;</hi> And now is the Lords own choſen remnant to be gathered in, and now is he making up of his Jewels, with whom he will dwell, and he is chuſing of a <hi>Peculiar people,</hi> who ſhall worſhip him <hi>in ſpirit</hi> out of all Shews and Shadows, Forms, Cuſtomes, and Traditions of men; And all Forms, and Cuſtomes, and Shadows of things ſhall be laid waſt, I ſay it ſhall be laid waſt, the Lord God will do it, his own mouth hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, <hi>the day is at hand wherein our God will work Wonders,</hi> I ſay the day is at hand wherein our God will work Wonders amongſt the Children of men, and amongſt all that dwell on the Earth will he make known his <hi>Arm of ſtrength,</hi> and his Power ſhall be ſeen, and his Miracles ſhall be made manifeſt, to the view of all the Inhabitants of the Earth; <hi>Babylons</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhall trade no more in that day, their lying devina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall ceaſe, the Lord will raiſe up Paſtors, and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after his own heart, ſuch as ſhall feed his people with knowledge and with underſtanding; but ſuch as go on in their lyes, which makes Merchandize of the Juſt, and ſtarves the ſouls of many, which deceives the ſimple, and cauſeth the weak to err in Judgement, a day of bitter torments is prepared for them, endleſs miſery ſhall come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, ſhe with all her Merchants and their Merchandizes ſhall fall, and her downfal muſt be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35572:4"/>great, ſhe that hath <hi>long ſat as a Queen,</hi> which ſaid ſhe ſhould ſee no ſorrow, ſhe I ſay muſt be thrown down, and all her good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Children with her, which lean upon her knees, they muſt be taken Captive together, ſhe hath Captivated and killed the Saints, and hath drunken the blood of the Innocent, ſhe muſt be led into captivity, ſhe that hath led others, ſhe muſt have blood for blood, as ſhe hath done to others, others muſt do to her, her very lovers ſhall loath her, none of them ſhall pitty her, the fire of Gods wrath ſhall conſume her fleſh; ſhame ſhall cover their faces who have taken pleaſure in her beauty, her fame ſhall be taken away, her glory ſhall utterly be defaced, her Foundation ſhal be rooted up, her Memorial ſhall utterly rot and be conſumed from off the face of the whole Earth, <hi>the Lord God Almighty hath ſpoken it, and it ſhall come to paſſe, and be fulfilled in its ſeaſon;</hi> Therefore howle all you that dwel on the Earth, I ſay howle all you who are yet in your ſins, be you afflicted and mourn and weep, let your laughter and ſinging be turned into mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and your Joy into heavineſſe, let ſhame cover your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, you proud wanton ones, is it not high time for you to conſider your wayes, and to ceaſe from that which is evil? O return whiles you have yet a day, remember you are but fleſh, and all fleſh is as graſſe, or as a flower of the field, who appeareth beautiful for a time, and in a moment is changed, or withered away, and you muſt dye; You know not how ſoon it may be, before the Lord may call you to an account, and then what will you ſay for your ſelves? You who have ſpent your time in Wantonneſſe, Pride, Vain laughter and fooliſh talking, in ſinging of Songs and Ballats, and telling of Stories, and taking Gods holy Name in vain, in Swearing, Lying and Drunkenneſſe, to the abuſing of the Creation of God, and many other laſcivious actions; Take warning, O be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, prize your time, make better uſe of it whiles the day of mercy laſteth, let a true Reformation be known amongſt you, Repent, Repent, put ſack-cloath upon your loyns and wallow in aſhes, let a true mournful ſtate in the ſight of the Lord God be known &amp; witneſſed amongſt you, that the Lord God may take pitty and compaſſion on you; <hi>Nineveh</hi> that great City, who went on in wickedneſs for a time, was warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35572:4"/>by one of the Lords Servants, as you may read in <hi>Jonah,</hi> and they received the Lords meſſage without queſtioning of it, and the <hi>Nenivites</hi> repented before the Lord, for the evil of their wayes, and the Lord was intreated by them, and he took pitty upon them and ſpared the City.</p>
            <p>And now O Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Waymouth,</hi> there is a neceſſity laid upon me at this time to warn you, becauſe of the evil day which muſt aſſuredly come upon all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity, but you have made leight of the many warnings of the Lord and of his Meſſengers, and ſome of them you have requited with cruel mockings, and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other ill uſage. O people conſider of theſe things, the Lord doth not uſually bring deſtruction, or ſore judgements, or plagues upon a People or Nation, but he firſt warns them of the evil that is to come upon them unleſs they repent. <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorab</hi> had a day wherein the Lord warned them of the evil that was to come upon them, but they ſleighted the Lords warning; O read, ſudden deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction came upon them; How could I take up a lamentation over thee O <hi>Waymouth, Waymouth?</hi> How could I take up a ſore lamentation over thee? How could I mourn over thee <hi>O Waymouth?</hi> Lamentable is thy ſtate, mournful is thy dayes, I am bowed down for thee, I have mourned for thee many times, as I have paſſed through thy ſtreets, tears have trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down mine eyes, to conſider the ſad eſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of many of thy Inhabitants, the Lord God hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie againſt you, the cry of oppreſſion is found amongſt you; O I have born the weight and burthen of many of your iniquities upon my own ſhoulders, the yoak of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion have lain heavy upon my neck, I have born a great burthen for you dayes without number; O the Seed of God lies oppreſt in you all, Profeſſors and Prophane; O the Seed of God, the Immortal Babe, the Begotten of God lies oppreſt in you all, not heeded nor regarded, although it cries aloud in you, and often groans by reaſon of your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; O you bruiſe the tender Principle of God in you all, and you put him to open ſhame daily, he who was the man of ſorrows, who was well acquainted with grief, whoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was mared more then any mans, he is oppreſſed in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35572:5"/>you all and by you; Read the little Babe, the begotten of God, he was laid in a Manger, in the worſt place of the Inn, the beaſt fed over the Babe, it lay in the Manger, I ſpeak near to you all, the beaſtly nature which was the firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward nature is not yet caſt out of many of you, the Babe lies under in you, the firſt nature lives above it, and this nature makes merry over the juſt, the little one that is low whom you tread over. And now in the fear of God I warn you all who ever you are that are out of the Truth of the living God, come down, come down to the true witneſs of God placed in you all, which makes manifeſt ſin and evil in the hearts and conſciences in every man and woman, and this is pure of God which makes manifeſt every man and womans ſtate and condition, and this is not of man nor of woman, although it is placed in man and in woman, but this ſtands in every man and woman as a faithful Witneſſe for God againſt ſin and evil, and this witneſs cannot conſent to any thing that is evil, which men and women does, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though men and women acts and walks contrary day after day to the leadings of this true witneſs, and where this true witneſs which God hath placed to be man and womans guide, I ſay, where and in whomſoever this true witneſs is not obeyed, loved nor believed in, by ſuch it is crucified and ſlain, and ſo Scripture comes to be fulfilled, as it was ſaid in a certain place in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> [ſpiritually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led] <hi>was our Lord Jeſus crucified and ſlain,</hi> and this ſhall be every mans and womans great condemnation, that <hi>light</hi> is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather then the light becauſe their deeds are evil; Now this witneſſe which makes every man and womans ſtate and conditions manifeſt, is <hi>light,</hi> and this light is <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Son of the living God, who was Crucified and ſlain by the blood-thirſty chief Prieſts and Rulers, who took councel together againſt him; And this Lord Jeſus who was ſpiritually abuſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ungodly Generation, the ſame is he which is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and come in the fleſh, with power and great glory, for the remiſſion of ſins, and for the juſtification of many, and alſo for the Condemnation of the wicked who know not God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35572:5"/>
Now that which is to be known of God, is manifeſt <hi>within</hi> every man and womans heart, the word is nigh <hi>in the heart, and in the mouth,</hi> look not abroad, for it is not without you, <hi>it is in you,</hi> make no delay, come to a ſearch, <hi>the pearl of great price</hi> lies hid <hi>in you,</hi> you muſt dig deep to find it, you muſt ſell your own wayes, your own wiſdom, your own will worſhips muſt you part withall, your worldly delights muſt be thrown aſide, if everyon come to find the pearl which lies hid <hi>in you,</hi> or to know the true wiſdom which God giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the whole heart muſt be ſwept and thorowly ſearcht, if ever the groat [which is loſt] be found; The Widow loſt the piece of ſilver in her own houſe, and with a candle ſhe ſearched till ſhe had found it [mark] the Widow ſearcht with the <hi>light</hi> in her own houſe for her loſt ſilver, ſhe did not ſearch in the dark, nor out of her own houſe, but ſhe ſearcht with a candle in her own houſe, till her loſt was found; All to the light come, every one in your own particulars, who are out of the truth of God, who are yet in your ſins, and in your iniquities, come forth to the true tryal, bring your deeds to the light, for the ſame Lord Jeſus who enlightneth every one that cometh into the world, is the true way which leads to the Kingdom of God; Now all you who are ſeeking the way of the Lord out of the <hi>light,</hi> you are out of the way, you are in darkneſs, and the true way of life there you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to find, the way which leads to Gods Kingdom is but one, and that is a ſtreight narrow way, ſo that none but the children of the <hi>light</hi> are able to paſs that way, the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites can never walk in the ſtreight narrow way, ſuch as are out of the <hi>light</hi> knows not the power of God to guide them, but they are in the many wayes, wherein is confuſion, and ſuch are talking and ſound worſhipping of an unknown God, who are out of the <hi>light,</hi> life and power of God, ſuch know not the true teachings of God, for they have not heard his voice at any time, nor ſeen his ſhape; and how can ſuch know the teachings of the Lord who are in darkneſs, and out of the life and power of God, who know not his voice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſeen his ſhape, but walk in the imaginations of their own hearts, ſuch are found in the broad way which leads to deſtruction, but the Children of the <hi>light</hi> and of the day,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35572:6"/>the ſheep of the true ſhepheard of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they know his voice, they know him and follow him, and ſtrangers they know and cannot follow, and to them he gives eternal life, and ſuch can never be pluckt out of his Fathers hand, and ſuch comes to know the true teachings of the Lord God, who knows his voice and are led and guided by it; but all you who are found ſcoffing at the <hi>light,</hi> O you are found fighting againſt the Lord, you would go in another way into the true ſheep-fold then by the <hi>Door;</hi> but ſuch are thieves which would murther the ſheep, ſuch cannot enter into the true ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold of reſt, where the whole flock of God finds paſture.</p>
            <p>And now all you who are yet in your ſins &amp; iniquities, who know not the power of God to guide you, I ask you where there is not ſuch a thing in you all, when you are upon your beds, or alone ſeparated from company, when you are cool and calm, I ſay at ſuch a time, is there not ſuch a thing in you, which brings your ſins to remembrance, and ſpreads them in order before you? Yea the ſins of your youth it brings to remembrance, and this ſhews you the danger of ſin many times before ever you have committed them, and this often ſtrives with you to preſerve you from ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and from doing that which is evil; but I ſay to you as I have already ſaid, where this true witneſſe is not obeyed, by ſuch it is crucified and put to open ſhame; therefore I ſay to you again in the fear of the living God, deal faithfully &amp; plainly with your ſelves, you who have any honeſt deſires to know the true way of the Lord, bring your deeds to the <hi>light,</hi> try your wayes there, give not ſleep to your eyes, nor ſlumber to your eye-lids, till you know how the condition ſtands with you; if you are in your ſins, the light will diſcover it to you as you in faithfulneſs to the Lord keep, whileſt you are in your ſins, this will ſpeak trouble to you, <hi>For there is no peace to the wicked ſaith my God,</hi> and if you live in your ſins, then ſin lies at the door, and your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will condemn you; and if ſin lies at the door, how then dares any of you to pray, or ſing, or ſacrifice your will-worſhips to the Lord? Doth he regard the many prayers of the wicked? Are they not abomination to him? Is it not required <hi>That all thoſe which nameth the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35572:6"/>muſt depart from iniquity?</hi> Or can the dead praiſe the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God? I mean ſuch as are dead in their ſins whiles they are alive.</p>
            <p>O deceive not yourſelves, God will not be mocked, ſuch as you ſow, ſuch ſhall you reap; if you ſow to the fleſh, you ſhall reap Condemnation, Wo and Miſery, the Lord hath no pleaſure in the prayers or praiſes of the wicked, the Lord is wearied of ſuch ſervices, or ſuch ſacrifices they have an ill ſavour in them: To Obedience all come, for Obedience is better then ſacrifice, it is truth in the inward parts which the Lord our God requires; And I ſay again to you, who hath any honeſt deſires after the Lord, be not wilfully blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, come out of your ſins, live no longer in them, for the wages of ſin is death, O come to him that makes an end of ſin, and deſtroyes the Devils works in man, the Fountain is open for ſin and for uncleanneſſe, it hath this virtue in it, it maketh clean the heart and conſcience of the Children of men, it purgeth from dead works, it doth not purge people from ſome of their ſins, and leave the reſt behind, but the blood of Jeſus clenſeth from <hi>all ſins,</hi> although many of you ſay, and your Teachers tell you and Teach you that you can never be freed from your ſins whileſt you are here, then I ſay to you all, as I have received it from the Lord, you ſhall never be made free from your ſins at all, but if you die in your ſins, you ſhall periſh eternally in them; For after death comes Judgement, and in the Grave there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and in the Pit remiſſion of ſins is not to be found; Therefore I ſay it upon you in the fear of God, all people what ever you are, Profeſſors or Prophance, prize your time whileſt you have it, leaſt repentance be hid from your eyes, and darkneſs come upon you unawares, for in the night none can work.</p>
            <p>Man was made after the Image of God, Created was he in purity and holineſſe, but when man diſobeyed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord, he loſt his pure Image, and ſo man became lyable to the wrath and curſe of God, and becauſe man went out into the diſobedience, he was driven out from the preſence of the Lord God; now man is in the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated eſtate in the ſeparation, gone from his Maker, driven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35572:7"/>out from the preſence of the Lord God, man hath loſt his dominion over the Creatures, by breaking Gods holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and for mans Tranſgreſſions was the flaming ſword placed in the midſt of the Garden, which turned eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way to keep the way of the tree of Life, the tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was the forbidden fruit, (mark) all man-kind hath fallen in <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt man, they have loſt their Image, they are in the Separation, in the Alienated Eſtate, gone from the Lord God, quite driven out from his pure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, they have all fed upon the tree forbidden, the tree of Knowledge which makes wiſe, the Serpents meat is fed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for which cauſe the ground was curſt, man is in the curſt ground, whileſt he ſtands in the Alienation from God, the curſt nature ſtands in him, it bears rule in him, and hath dominion over him, ſo that it leadeth him into Captivity to the law of ſin and death; Now all men and women, who hath been in the fallen eſtate can never come to God again, but as they poſſe through the flaming ſword, which God hath placed in the Garden, to keep the way of the tree of life; I ſpeak near to the underſtandings of people, that ſo if any are willing to be undeceived, they may know and read what I ſay; (mark) there is none I ſay can ever come to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but as they come through the flaming ſword, the firſt forward nature, which hath led all men and women into the ſeparation from God muſt be ſlain by ſire and ſword, the wrath of God muſt be known to paſſe upon the head of that Nature which led out into the Tranſgreſſion, there is nothing which is unclean or unholy that leads into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration muſt be kept alive, that which is for the ſword muſt be cut down by the ſword, and that which is for the fire muſt be deſtroyed by the fire of Gods wrath and vengeance; and this I ſay whoſoever comes to God again to have their Image renewed in the Kingdome of God, muſt paſſe thorow great Troubles, Tryals and Tribulations, ſuch as hath not been known ſince the World began, till the old Nature which is the Image of the old man, I ſay till that Nature is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, true peace is not to be known, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I came not to bring peace on the Farth but a ſword firſt,</hi> and ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and this ſword maketh an end of ſin, and cuts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35572:7"/>down and deſtroyes the Devils Nature in men and women, which hath long bore rule in their hearts, and had the Dominion over them; Now all you who are in the fallen eſtate, try your deeds by the <hi>Light,</hi> that your dark underſtandings may be opened, <hi>come forth to the Lords Battel, all you who are at eaſe in the fleſh,</hi> the battell is begun, and the wo of the Lord is againſt all ſuch who are at eaſe; All upon your guard ſtand, every man to his watch, diligence is required of all people, prove and ſee if any of you have known a day of ſlaughter upon the man of ſin, and if you have not known a day of ſlaughter upon the man of ſin, then I ſay to you all in Gods fear, it is not ſafety for any of you to ſit down ſatisfied, or to give eaſe to your fleſh, till you know your iniquities forgiven you, and your ſins blotted out, and removed and done away as a thick Cloud; And this is to be done in man, felt and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in man and woman, the Marriage day is come wherein many are eſpouſed to one Husband, Chriſt Jeſus the <hi>Lamb</hi> of life which taketh away the ſins of the World, he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Teacher of his people, ſo that they need not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to teach them; and here the woman is known to learn wiſdome of her Husband at home, and not to aske it of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the woman is to learn in ſilence of her Husband, Chriſt the Husband and head of Male and Female, he who was from everlaſting to everlaſting, whoſe dayes are without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or ending, and this is he which guides and rules all the Children of the day, the babes begotten of God they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay the written word is their guide and rule, but they know and witneſſe him to guide and rule them which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an end of ſin and deſtroyes the Devils works. <hi>Wo to the falſe Teachers which teach lies, and lead the people in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known path, which the Lord God hath no pleaſure in, a bed of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is prepared for them, endleſſe miſery muſt come upon them unleſſe they ceaſe from deceiving the Lords people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For truth ſake I cannot reſt, and for the Seeds ſake I cannot hold my tongue, the Lord God hath ſpoken in me, how can I keep ſilence? He hath uttered his voice in me like a King going to the Battel, the Inſtruments for war is already prepared, the battel day is come, the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:35572:8"/>over all the whole earth, that the Nations may know him come to reign whoſe right it is, he that hath long been kept in bondage in a ſtrange Land under a ſtrange King, the <hi>Lamb</hi> of life is he called, the bright morning Star of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> which giveth light to thoſe that ſat in darkneſs, the <hi>Lamb</hi> of life ſhall reign as a King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all dark powers in Nations and Kingdoms ſhall bow and bend before him, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall faint to ſee his Authority, Kings ſhall be afraid when he appeareth to make known his power, a day of ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt come that many may ſee his Power; <hi>Sions</hi> redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on draweth nigh, let the little ones rejoyce, deliverance muſt be known to the captives, let the Babes ſing for joy, <hi>O land of Oppreſſors, you which lie in wait for blood, take heed to your wayes, look to it, the Lord God hath ſaid it, and it will aſſuredly come to paſſe,</hi> I ſay, the Lord God hath ſpoken it, <hi>that he will ſweep the land of oppreſſors, the beſom of deſtuction is in his hand, he will make men know that there is a God in</hi> Iſrael, &amp; he hath power to throw down, root up, ſcatter and deſtroy all that is not of his own building, planting, gathering or begetting, the ſtrength of man ſhall not hinder it, the powers of darkneſſe death and hell nor the Grave ſhall not hinder it; <hi>I will make my Miracles known, ſaith the Lord God Almighty,</hi> the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ols of my indignation will I ſwiftly pour out upon all that doth evil, I will make my Miracles known amongſt thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, I the Lord will ſtain the glory of man, I the Lord will ſtain mans Glory, I will daſh the Pot ſheards of the earth together one againſt another, and they ſhall be broken to pieces, and Bryars and Thorns muſt be burnt up, who are ſtanding together in battel againſt the Lord God of the whole earth. <hi>Wo to the Inhabitants of the Earth and of the Sea, for the Devil is come down in a rage, and hath but a ſhort time to Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35572:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
